exploit-exercises/protostar offers a linux image with several challenges to learn binary
利用练习/ProtoStar提供了一个Linux映像，它具有学习二进制文件的几个挑战
exploitation. But a lot has changed over the years and if you compile these challenges
剥削。但这些年来发生了很大的变化，如果你把这些挑战汇编起来
yourself on a modern system it’s not as easy anymore. I already showed you that in
你自己在一个现代的系统上，这不再是那么容易了。我已经给你看了
the previous videos about the stack challenge. I had to make a 3 part video series to explain
之前关于堆栈挑战的视频。我必须制作一个由三部分组成的视频系列来解释
how we can still do it. And that also only on 32bit. So if you are just starting out,
我们怎么还能做到。也只有32位。所以如果你刚开始，
make sure that you use the Linux image that you can download here and don’t compile
请确保使用可以在此处下载的Linux映像，不要编译
it yourself. Otherwise all the tutorials about it won’t work. And now for this video, let’s
这是你自己的。否则，所有关于它的教程都将不起作用。现在我们来看看这个视频
continue with some other challenge. We compile them on a current Ubuntu version, without
继续其他一些挑战。我们在当前的Ubuntu版本上编译它们，没有
any compile flags and see what we get.
any compile flags and see what we get.
Obviously the rules of the game, that is hacking, are, that maybe there are techniques I just
很明显，游戏规则，即黑客，是，也许有一些技术我只是
don’t know about. I don’t really know the edge cases in exploitation, I mostly know
不知道。我真的不知道剥削中的边缘案例，我主要知道
the general techniques and I think I have some reasonable amount of creativity. But
一般的技术和我认为我有一些合理的创造力。但是
I don’t know everything. So it’s likely that there are people out there that could
我什么都不知道。所以很可能有人可以
exploit it. In that case, I’d love to see a PoC for that. That being said, let’s continue
利用它。在这种情况下，我希望看到一个POC。尽管如此，让我们继续
with format0.
with format0.
So what is this challenge about? The attacker can pass in an argument, that argument is
那么这个挑战是关于什么的呢？攻击者可以传入一个参数，该参数是
then being passed as the string variable to the format parameter of sprintf. So we can
然后作为字符串变量传递给sprintf的格式参数。所以我们可以
inject stuff like %d or %s.
inject stuff like %d or %s.
It’s also vulnerable to a buffer overflow, because sprintf, does not print to the console,
它还容易受到缓冲区溢出的影响，因为sprintf不会打印到控制台，
to stdout, like regular printf, but prints, or stores the formatted string, in buffer.
to stdout, like regular printf, but prints, or stores the formatted string, in buffer.
And the buffer is only 64 bytes long.
And the buffer is only 64 bytes long.
Now when you attack this on the VM that you can download here that has these challenges
现在，当你在虚拟机上攻击它时，你可以在这里下载这些挑战
precompiled, the target variable would be placed after the buffer so that you can overflow
预编译后，目标变量将放在缓冲区之后，以便溢出
the buffer, and write into target. And then you have target modified and when you make
缓冲区，并写入目标。然后你修改了目标，当你
it so that it’s overflown with 0xdeadbeef you pass this check.
it so that it’s overflown with 0xdeadbeef you pass this check.
So enter 64characters, and 0xdeadbeef and you won.
So enter 64characters, and 0xdeadbeef and you won.
But the challenge here also said, try it with less than 10 bytes. And you would do that
但是这里的挑战也说，用少于10字节的字节来尝试。你会这么做的
by abusing format string modifiers that would stretch the formatted output to for example
例如，通过滥用格式字符串修饰符将格式化输出拉伸到
64 characters, and then you can simply enter 0xdeadbeef afterwards. So for example %64d
64个字符，然后您可以简单地输入0xdeadbeef。例如%64d
would output a number with a up to 64 character padding. And so 64 characters plus 0xdeadbeef
将输出一个最多可填充64个字符的数字。所以64个字符加上0个死肉
are written into buffer and you win.
are written into buffer and you win.
Well is that still possible?
好吧，那还有可能吗？
First we have to install gcc and gdb on this fresh maschine and I’m also going ahead
首先，我们必须在这个新鲜的吉祥物上安装gcc和gdb，我还要继续
to install peda, a gdb extension that makes things look nicer.
to install peda, a gdb extension that makes things look nicer.
So let’s start with the simple buffer overflow example. But first let’s set a breakpoint
所以让我们从简单的缓冲区溢出示例开始。但首先让我们设置一个断点
in vuln() before we compare deadbeef. Then let’s start the binary and pass in an input
在Vuln（）中，在我们比较死肉之前。然后让我们启动二进制文件并传入一个输入
that is much larger than 64bytes. Okay. So we hit the breakpoint and it compares eax
这比64字节大得多。可以。所以我们碰到了断点，它比较EAX
with 0xdeadbeef. But eax is 0. How can that be? Didn’t we overflow the stack?
和0块牛肉。但是EAX是0。怎么会这样？我们不是溢出了堆栈吗？
Well, we certainly did, the issue is that the target variable doesn’t come after the
当然，问题是目标变量不在
buffer. It is before, so we can write as much data as we want, we won’t overwrite target.
buffer. It is before, so we can write as much data as we want, we won’t overwrite target.
You can also see this here. Eax is loaded from base pointer - 0x54, while the address
你也可以在这里看到这个。EAX从基指针-0x54加载，而地址
for the string is loaded from basepointer - 0x50, so it’s located after target.
for the string is loaded from basepointer - 0x50, so it’s located after target.
Well does this mean it’s not exploitable?
这是否意味着它不可利用？
mmhh... So if you are familiar with format string exploits, you also know that you can
嗯…因此，如果您熟悉格式字符串漏洞，您也知道可以
write data with it, by abusing the %n modifier which writes the amount of already printed
使用它写入数据，方法是滥用写已打印数量的%n修饰符
characters to an address on the stack. And we can overflow the stack, so we could place
字符到堆栈上的地址。我们可以溢出堆栈，这样我们可以
an address there and then carefully construct the number of characters printed before, such
一个地址，然后仔细地构造之前打印的字符数，例如
that it writes 0xdeadbeef to an address. And so we could write to target, and win that
它把0个死区写到一个地址。所以我们可以写信给目标公司，然后赢了。
way, right?
路，对吧？
But ASLR is our problem. Let me add a printf to the code to print the address of target.
But ASLR is our problem. Let me add a printf to the code to print the address of target.
ampercant target returns the reference of a variable, so that’s the address.
ampercant target returns the reference of a variable, so that’s the address.
And when we compile it and run it in a nice while true loop, you see how crazy the address
当我们编译它并在一个很好的循环中运行它时，你会发现这个地址有多疯狂
of target changes. Target is a local variable so it’s located on the stack. So this is
目标更改。目标是一个局部变量，因此它位于堆栈上。所以这就是
also a stack address. But how much does it change? It always starts
也是一个堆栈地址。但它能改变多少呢？它总是开始
with 0x7ff and ends in a C. And this one nibble here only appears to be C,D,E or F. That’s
以0x7FF结尾的是C。这里的这一个咬边似乎只有C、D、E或F。那是
a huge number. It’s over 1 billion. but maybe in this case actually doable. Just takes
一个巨大的数字。超过10亿。但在这种情况下，也许是可行的。只需要
some time. Maybe a day or so. I just like to refer to the previous three part video
一些时间。也许一天左右吧。我只想看前面的三部分视频
where we bruteforced a 3 byte stack cookie, that was roughly 16 million possible options.
where we bruteforced a 3 byte stack cookie, that was roughly 16 million possible options.
And so here, 260 million, is in reach, I would say. At least for a very small binary like
因此，我想说，在这里，2.6亿美元的资金即将到位。至少对于非常小的二进制
this. The execution speed is quite fast. Let’s see how it looks like on 32bit. We
这个。执行速度比较快。让我们看看32位的情况。我们
have to install the gcc multilib to do that. And then we can compile it with -m32.
have to install the gcc multilib to do that. And then we can compile it with -m32.
When we execute it a few times, you can see that it obviously has less randomness than
当我们执行它几次时，你可以看到它的随机性明显低于
on 64bit. It’s only two full bytes and then again a nibble. That’s about 1 million attempts
64位。它只有两个全字节，然后又是一个半字节。大约100万次尝试
to hit it. So definitely even more in reach. But of course it’s only feasible if you
击中它。所以，它的触角肯定更大。当然，只有当你
can do millions of attempts reasonably fast, for example locally. If this were an application
可以以相当快的速度完成数百万次尝试，例如在本地。如果这是一个申请
that takes longer to start or a remote service, then that would probably mean you couldn’t
启动或远程服务需要更长的时间，这可能意味着您无法
really do it.
really do it.
How to create a format string exploit and how that exactly works with %n you can watch
如何创建一个格式字符串漏洞，以及它如何与%n一起工作，您可以观看
in multiple other videos that I have done. But there is one additional trick that comes
在我做过的其他多个视频中。但还有另外一个技巧
to mind we could look out for. So to write with %n we expect the target address to be
注意，我们可以小心。所以要用%n写入，我们希望目标地址是
on the stack. In a classic format string exploit you would use your input that is maybe also
在堆栈上。在一个经典的格式字符串漏洞中，您可能会使用
placed on the stack and reference itself. But nobody says it has to be an address you
放置在堆栈上并引用自身。但没人说一定是你的地址
place there, the stack is full of values, maybe you get lucky. If we look on the stack
放在那里，堆满了价值观，也许你走运了。如果我们看看那堆
when we are at the 0xdeadbeef compare in the execution flow, you can see a lot of stack
当我们在执行流中进行0xdeadbeef比较时，可以看到很多堆栈
addresses. And so these would always be valid stack addresses even with ASLR. Now if one
地址。因此，即使使用aslr，这些堆栈地址也是有效的。如果现在
of those would magically point to target, then we could just reuse it. We could just
其中的一个会神奇地指向目标，然后我们就可以重用它了。我们可以
reference that address. But if we check the address we know of target,
参考那个地址。但是如果我们查一下我们知道的目标地址，
we can see that it doesn’t show up. Oh well. But you see how creative you can get with
我们可以看到它没有出现。哦，好吧。但你看你能有多大的创造力
exploitation. We could have been lucky. But let’s actually continue that train of
剥削。我们本可以走运的。但让我们继续
thought. Ok we don’t have the whole target address
思想。好吧，我们没有完整的目标地址
on the stack, but we do have a lot of other stack addresses. And we have an overflow,
在堆栈上，但是我们有很多其他堆栈地址。我们有一个溢出，
so we can overflow into the addresses. And just overwrite some low bytes and keep the
所以我们可以溢出到地址中。只需覆盖一些低字节并保留
whole front. Let’s add another printf to print the target
整个正面。我们再添加一个printf来打印目标
value. And print the resulting formatted buffer. And let’s play with that. Here you can see
价值。并打印生成的格式化缓冲区。让我们一起玩。在这里你可以看到
the sprintf formatted result. Let try to find AAAABBBB on the stack by consuming
sprintf格式的结果。让我们尝试通过消费在堆栈上找到aabbb
values from the stack with someformat modifiers. I wanna find the offset where on the stack
堆栈中带有someformat修饰符的值。我想找到叠层上的偏移位置
this value is placed, and we can explore that with %lx and the dollar notation.So at stack
这个值被放置，我们可以用%lx和美元符号来探索它。
offset 1 it’s not, at offset 2 it’s not at offset 3 it’s not. And so forth. But
偏移量1不是，偏移量2不是偏移量3不是。诸如此类。但是
here at offset 9 we now printed the hex value of our input.
here at offset 9 we now printed the hex value of our input.
Now let’s look at the stack layout for a nice stack address we could partially overwrite.
Now let’s look at the stack layout for a nice stack address we could partially overwrite.
Ok so down here is one, let’s see what offset that has. Let’s keep going.
Ok so down here is one, let’s see what offset that has. Let’s keep going.
There it is, at offset 19. Which also means from the start at offset
在那里，偏移19。这也意味着从偏移开始
9 to offset 19 we have 10 groups of 8 bytes, so 80 bytes to fill and reach this value.
9 to offset 19 we have 10 groups of 8 bytes, so 80 bytes to fill and reach this value.
We can achieve that with a format string that pads a number to 80 bytes, and then some input
我们可以通过一个填充数字到80字节的格式字符串来实现这一点，然后使用一些输入
to proof that we overflow. And when we now execute it, we see that the
以证明我们溢出了。当我们现在执行它时，我们看到
end of our address that got printed by our 19 lx, got overwritten with As.
end of our address that got printed by our 19 lx, got overwritten with As.
If you paid attention you saw that target is always at an offset with a c, so we can
如果你注意到了，你会发现目标总是在C的偏移处，所以我们可以
choose some input that ends’ with a C as well to overwrite it. For example L, that
选择一些以“c”结尾的输入并覆盖它。例如，l，
is 0x4c. Let’s execute that now, and you can compare
是0x4c。现在让我们执行它，您可以比较
what address we got now through the overwrite with L, and what target really was. You see
我们现在通过覆盖l得到了什么地址，真正的目标是什么。你看
that often it’s not the same, but eventually, it will match.
that often it’s not the same, but eventually, it will match.
And so if we replace the %lx to print a 8 byte hex value to %n, then we will WRITE to
因此，如果我们替换%lx以将8字节十六进制值打印到%n，那么我们将写入
that address. So now we are writing the amount of printed
那个地址。所以现在我们写的是
characters, 81, because 80 + the single L to this address. And maybe at some point we
字符，81，因为80+单个L到这个地址。也许在某个时候我们
hit target. Let’s keep trying. BOOM! There we hit target, we wrote 0x51 to
击中目标。我们继续努力吧。繁荣！在那里我们击中了目标，我们写了0x51
it, which is 81 in decimal. And that works fairly reliably, we can try those few attempts
它的小数点是81。这是相当可靠的，我们可以尝试这几次尝试
by hand. And I think that’s awesome, unfortunately
用手。我觉得那太棒了，不幸的是
it’s not quite the solution, because target has to be 0xdeadbeef. And that’s 3 billion
这不完全是解决方案，因为目标必须是0xdeadbeef。那是30亿
in decimal. So with this technique we would have to first print 3 billion characters before
十进制。因此，使用这种技术，我们必须先打印30亿个字符
we can do %n, and that’s not possible.
we can do %n, and that’s not possible.
Anyway I think you can see how much exploitation can become a puzzle that you slowly try to
不管怎样，我认为你可以看到有多少剥削可以成为你慢慢尝试的一个难题。
piece together. In the end I didn’t manage to solve it but exploring this was really
拼凑在一起。最后我没能解决，但探索这个问题
fun. I really wonder if somebody is able to make
乐趣。我真想知道是否有人能
a semi reliable exploit for this.
a semi reliable exploit for this.